Swadishthan, Thinking, Illness Part 2, Sydney, Australia, 19900316
I bow to all the seekers of truth.
I’m happy you all are enjoying this music and this dancing,
and about these artists, I have to say that after coming to Sahaja Yoga,
at a very young age, they achieved such mastery.
Because, when the Kundalini rises, as I told you,
She enriches your centres.
The centre about which I was going to talk to you today is the centre of creativity,
which looks after your power of action, physical and mental.
This power of action moves on the right side of the spinal cord
and coming to the optic chiasma, it crosses over,
passes to the left side and creates an institution called ego.
The institution of ego is a myth.
What we do is to get something dead, like some trees dead,
so make some platform or some furniture.
We take some stones and make a hall,
and we think we have done a great job.
Actually, what we have done is to reconstructed the dead.
But while doing it, we get the feeling that we have done it, something.
That is how our ego develops.
This channel on the right-hand side caters to your future.
So those people who plan too much, think too much,
exhaust the energy of this centre
because this centre has the first responsibility
to convert the fat cells in the stomach for the use of the brain,
which is overused, to make them into grey cells.
So, when you start thinking too much,
it has to work more for this very important function.
When it starts working for one function,
the other functions are neglected.
And the other functions are:
it has to cater, to nourish or to give energy to your liver,
to your pancreas, to your spleen, to your kidneys and part of your intestine.
So, once you start neglecting these organs,
first your liver suffers.
Means, the function of liver gets limited.
The function basically of the liver, basically, is
to absorb the heat of the body which is the poison
and allow it to permeate into the bloodstream.
But the energy is so limited that it cannot function properly.
So, this centre starts neglecting liver
and liver then cannot get rid of all the heat of the body,
so the heat starts flowing upward.
When it starts flowing upward, then there’s a centre,
what you call as the Right Heart, which gets affected.
People develop a disease called asthma with it.
Also, they develop a disease
what you call as a massive heart attack, on the left-hand side,
when the heat reaches there.
They also can develop a paralysis of the right side
when it reaches the brain.
The vulnerability is there.
And then it’s triggered somehow by the left side action, maybe.
Such people are futuristic, they go on planning for the future.
Future doesn’t exist, only the present is the truth.
But they go on planning about future, waste their energies
and ultimately find that all their plans fail.
One must know the Divine plan.
If you know the Divine plan, then you don’t have to plan
because you know the Divine is already planning for you everything.
When you understand after Realisation that everything is done
by Paramchaitanya, by this All-Pervading Power, by this Ruh,
then you do not think that you are doing something.
Moreover, as I told you,
when the Kundalini rises through the Agnya Chakra,
both these institutions of ego and superego are sucked in,
so there is no ego, so you become egoless,
so your karmas or your duties or your so-called work
you have done become akarmas.
Then you don’t talk like this,
that “I have done this, I have done that.”
They say, “Oh it’s rising, it’s happening, it’s working out.”
You start speaking in the third person.
Even sometimes children you will find they talk like that.
“This little boy won’t go because it is obstinate.” They’ll talk about themselves.
If you notice, if they’re realised souls, they’ll talk like that,
in the third person.
So, you become a third person.
And nourishment to this centre comes through your Realisation
as the Kundalini is connected to the mains.
As a result, you get into balance.
You are in thoughtless awareness.
Somebody has asked Me about the thinking, yesterday.
So, the thought arises from the past or from the future.
As we have a capacity to react,
because of the construction of our body as a prism.
It’s a little scientific thing, but if you listen to some of My lectures,
you’ll understand what I mean.
Now what happens, when you see something, you react,
anything you see, you react. You see this carpet, you’ll react.
You’ll see this mic, you’ll react. You’ll think something about it.
So, a thought comes either from the future or from the past
and there’s a wave of thought coming and going,
again thought coming and going. It comes and disappears.
In between these thoughts, there’s a little space which is the present.
But if I say "you pay attention to yourself, to your present",
you cannot, unless and until you are a realised soul.
So, when the Kundalini rises, these thoughts become –
they lean out, means they become thin.
When they become thin, the space in between increases
and that’s how you become thoughtlessly aware.
So, the thinking is minimised,
then the liver doesn’t have to do all the time the job of converting
your fat cells into grey cells.
It comes into balance.
Then the second one is the pancreas. That is neglected, too.
In a person who is futuristic, who thinks too much, plans too much,
that also becomes neglected.
Now, the function of the pancreas is to absorb
the sugar into bloodstream in a proper way.
But because it is neglected, it has a very limited energy,
it cannot function, so you get diabetes.
Because of too much thinking, you get diabetes.
As I told you yesterday that in India, if you have to give tea to someone,
be careful if he is from a village,
because in the village, you have to put so much sugar
that the spoon should stand at right angles. Otherwise, it’s no tea for them.
And they never get diabetes, never get diabetes.
Diabetes is the headache of the people who sit on chairs, write,
think,worry and are time bound.
All such people get diabetes. They’re futuristic,
egoistical, arrogant, hot-tempered.
And such people get also heart attacks which are of a massive nature.
The Left Heart is connected in a way,
when there’s too much of exertion on the physical side also
one can get heart attack.
The another type of heart attack one gets is angina,
that’s due to some other reason, that’s due to the lethargic heart.
So now we have another problem which is very serious is that of the spleen.
Spleen is the speedometer. It’s the one that gives us rhythm.
If we are rhythmic in life, spleen keeps all right.
But we are very hectic.
And the function of the spleen is to create red blood corpuscles
whenever there is an emergency.
So, the way we are, we are always under a shock.
Early in the morning you get up, what do you see?
You read the newspaper, horrid news.
I mean newspapers have to give horrid news, they never give good news, you know.
They say, “We don’t want to say if some plane has landed safely.”
But if there’s a disaster, so many have died, killed in action,
murders, horrible things, naturally you get a shock,
because you are a human being and in a subconscious you feel,
in unconscious area, you get the jerk. There’s a shock.
Then you start
the day in a hectic way, you are time-bound, you have to rush,
you can’t take your breakfast, you just take something, grab,
rush to the car or maybe on anything
and then you find the jam in modern days.
Everything keeps you on a tension. Then you reach the office,
there’s the boss who’s getting angry with you because you’re late.
As it is, I don’t know how much work we really produce.
Only the mess we have created in this world, I think,
much more in the modern times than much work.
We cannot have people like Mozart nowadays,
we can’t have anyone like Michelangelo,
we cannot have any artists who can create beautiful things,
we do not have beautiful buildings now, horrible, plastics.
We cannot have beautiful, artistic clothes.
Everything is becoming plastic and for which,
we are working so very hard to create plastic mountains.
All this leads to tensions, so we become tense.
And the tensions go on increasing as this ego increases,
covers all your head and you go into tension.
But the worst thing that happens to you that this spleen
which is the one responsible for keeping the rhythm of your life, goes hectic
and becomes crazy, doesn’t understand what sort of a personality you are.
Sometimes you rush to that, sometimes you rush to that.
There’s no rhythm in the life.
So, it gets upset
and it starts producing red blood corpuscles unrhythmically,
it doesn’t know. So, the vulnerability is there.
And as soon as there’s any triggering from the left side,
you develop a horrible disease called blood cancer,
and the only treatment you can have in the medical science is that
you’ll be certified that you’ll die after eight days or after one month.
That’s the only possibility.
But, with Kundalini awakening, your own power nourishes this centre
and supplies energy, soothes down your hectic speedometer.
which is the spleen. and the disease gets cured.
There are many we know of who got their blood cancer cured
and even after six, seven years they’re living and kicking all right.
All this is available to you within yourself.
This is all been promised. Many great people have written about it.
It’s not that I’m saying something new. Only the new thing
we are seeing here is that you can get en masse Realisation.
Then is the kidney. Kidney also gets affected,
firstly by the heat of the liver, secondly
by the strenuous type of life you lead, futuristic, neglected,
and then you get blood pressures.
Blood pressures you get till you get failure of your kidneys
or you might get a paralysis, anything is possible.
So, we have blood pressure, high blood pressure.
All this is only because of one centre, when it is out of gear.
But if all the seven centres are out of gear,
what should happen to us?
And I think the modern life is such that it could be,
all centres could be in danger.
So, it is eminent, is important that we should get
our Kundalini awakened and we should enjoy the best health.
Health of course you enjoy very well, no doubt. But apart from health,
apart from health, apart from health,
you enjoy many other things. First of all, you enjoy yourself.
Today there’s no time to discuss all the centres, but still I would say
that I would like to give you all the benefits of Sahaja Yoga,
which are possible, that you start enjoying others.
You become righteous, as I told you,
and you start enjoying your virtues.
You are no more a critic of things. If you have to criticise,
you criticise yourself, laugh at yourself and you don’t laugh at others.
You start connecting yourself, if you have the art of Kundalini awakening,
because yoga means, of course, the union with the Divine.
Also means ‘yukti’, meaning ‘the deftness’,
deftness to raise the Kundalini of yours and of others.
If you know the decoding of these centres,
of these centres on your fingertips –
five, six and seven on the left side and five, six and seven on the right side –
if you just know the decoding, immediately you can do the diagnosis,
what is wrong basically with you, and you can correct it.
So physically, mentally, emotionally you can correct yourself;
and spiritually you ascend.
You ascend to a state of a saint, a sage.
And the time has come for us to become sages.
For that you don’t have to leave your homes, houses, run away from your families,
nothing. That’s an escape. You don’t have to suffer.
You have to enter into the Kingdom of God to enjoy
that beauty and bounty of His Love.
Now this balance is important within us.
There’s one more disease, a very common one in the West
is the cancer of the breast in the case of women, which comes from the centre of Heart.
The centre, there are three hearts according to Sahaja Yoga,
one is the Central Heart, one is Left and one Right.
Now the Central Heart is placed in the spinal cord,
below the sternum bone.
Sternum bone is the one that creates the antibodies till the age of twelve years.
And then they get distributed all over.
And these antibodies then fight all the emergencies
and overcome all the troubles for us,
but then they can become also very weak.
So, the remote control is in the sternum bone.
Now this centre is the centre of a Mother,
of the Primordial Mother, we can say,
of the Mother Who is the Mother of this Universe and Mother of this world,
Who looks after the security of children, security of the people.
When a woman is challenged in her motherhood,
supposing she is a wife of someone
and husband is giving her insecurities by any means,
supposing his is a wayward person or he’s always threatening her
or dominating her or challenging her,
her security gets disturbed and then this trouble starts.
Maybe her children, maybe anyone can give this insecurity to a woman
and that’s how she develops this cancer of the breast.
That also can be corrected if the Kundalini could be made to pass through
this centre and nourish it.
The centre that is the most important is the seventh centre.
The seventh centre is the centre which is placed
around the limbic area in the head,
which has got one thousand petals
and when enlightened, it looks like beautiful flames,
very wide flames just like petals of all the seven colours.
That’s why it is said in the Bible, “I’ll appear before you like flames.”
These are the flames, you see.
This is the most important thing because around the limbic area
are placed all the seats, governing seats of all the centres.
So, if this centre is fully opened out,
they all get drenched by the grace of the Divine Power
and the person really, really enjoys Sahaja Yoga
in the best possible way.
He’s a happy person, he’s a joyous person, he emits joy, he emits peace,
he’s compassionate, he’s tireless, he looks after people
and such a person can achieve great heights of purity within himself.
The another centre which is bestowed by Christ, as I told yesterday,
is the Agnya Chakra, which is also very important,
because Christ has said, “Thou shalt not have adulterous eyes.”
That’s what He has said it. You should find out among Christian nations,
how many have got such pure eyes.
Pure eyes means those who do not react, just witness, watch.
There’s no greed, there’s no lust in those eyes.
Such eyes are so powerful that even a glance of such an eye
can give salvation.
And this is what it is: we have to achieve the pure eyes.
Such pure eyes are the only one which give you the joy of seeing.
Of course, you’ll have the books, you can read them
and find out about all the centres and know about it.
But what we have to see is that the problems of the world are because of us.
We are the problems and we manifest the problems outside
which reflect back upon us like the waves come back
and dash against the shore and again are reflected back.
We have to, ourselves, get into the state of sages.
Then nobody has to tell you, “Do this” or “Do that.”
You become your own master, you become your own guru,
and you look after yourself.
I have to apologise for one thing,
that Sahaja Yoga started in Australia with a little jerk.
They were Australians who started it,
but they were not up to the mark, I must say they were not,
created lots of problem for us, lots of problems.
And we didn’t know what to do with them. It has happened nowhere
in the world as it has happened here.
I don’t know why it took lot of time for it to properly establish itself.
Thank God now we have people who are sensible
and I hope you will make it convenient after getting your Realisation
to establish yourself properly, establish yourself
and reach that state of Nirvikalpa, doubtless awareness.
If you have any problem, you should write to Me directly.
You don’t have to bear anything. Christ has already taken the cross upon Himself,
so we don’t have to do anything. If there’s any problem
that you find is not all right, you should write to Me
instead of getting disappointed or getting frustrated.
Is best is to write to Me. I know it’s far away, Australia is very far off.
But this is the land which is the land of purity.
This is the land in the universe is the first centre that you see there,
and Uluru that you have – Uluru means, as I told you, is the Chaitanya,
is the symbol of that purity.
So, you stand for the innocence of the world.
You are such a great nation here that stands for the innocence,
and you could be very gullible. So, you have to be careful
and understand your own identity as innocent people.
And I am sure it will work out very well for all of you.
And this country which has many problems will be solved
by your own purity and the whole world can be helped
with your own purity and beautiful lives.
May God bless you.
Yesterday we had too many questions.
Too many.
And I told you that by asking questions –
I can answer all of them, I think so,
but I cannot guarantee that if I answer you
that means I can give you awakening. It’s not guaranteed that way.
So, if you want to have your Realisation
and if there is any problem that stands between that Realisation and yourself,
then it is better you should ask Me some question.
It’s much better to save time.
[Is raising the Kundalini dangerous?]
Not at all. Kundalini is your Mother.
She’s your individual mother and She looks after you. She knows everything about you.
She’s taped everything that you have been doing, you have been desiring.
She knows everything about you
and She’s anxiously waiting to give you your second birth.
As your mother took up upon herself all the labour pains,
She takes all the troubles for Herself.
We have had so many people. I have never seen anyone getting into trouble.
This myth has been created by people who are money-oriented, I think,
who wanted to frighten you so that you don’t go to reality and pay them well.
[Could You define “Kundalini”?]
Yesterday I did. You came today only, madam? Oh, I see.
Kundalini is a power, as I told you, is a residual power,
is the fourth power within us which resides in the triangular bone
in three and a half coils.
And It rises through six centres, subtle centres.
This is the power of your pure desire.
All other desires are impure because they’re never satiable in general.
The only desire that is pure is to be one with the Divine.
[Hindi]
Nanak Sahib has described as surti.
Kabira especially has described it as surti.
But imagine human beings how they are.
Kabira was born in Bihar, most of his work was in Bihar.
Later on, he went to Punjab. And in Bihar, they call tobacco as surti.
Yes, in Bihar they do. It’s very surprising to call tobacco as surti.
So many things of Granth Sahib can only be understood
when you get your Self Realisation, otherwise you cannot.
Is said it [Hindi].
What is this apa? Is your Self. He is the one who has done the tremendous work on this.
Tremendous work on Kundalini, all of them, Namadeva.
Even to think of them is great.
[How is that you can control your ego and all that as well as the (...)]
Yah. This is the first temptation you have. Yah, yah, yah. Agreed with you
that it starts giving you ego if you are not
fully developed in Sahaja Yoga. This is the first temptation,
I know that. But people become very creative.
It has happened to many Sahaja Yogis I have seen,
they became very creative, they started producing lot of potteries
and things, and started producing beautiful paintings.
There was one Australian lady she produced very beautiful paintings
and she got, won fame and all that, and ego had blasted her completely.
And she came to see Me in Perth, I found such heat coming out of her,
like a cancer patient, absolutely like a cancer patient.
And then if you tell her, “You have got ego”, they don’t like it,
because they’re so egoistical.
That’s why, that's why, that's why  you have to take
the Kundalini always up there. You shouldn’t be satisfied.
You see, that’s the slipping point sometimes, so be careful, be careful.
Now look at these artists, they are so simple.
Our attention should be, “What have I attained in Sahaja Yoga?
Is my spiritual ascent”. This is just a temptation,
one of the temptations that people have.
That’s not so important.
Now for these artists, the most important thing is just to play for Me,
that’s all.
[You say we shouldn’t plan too much. Could You explain
that because obviously we need to plan a little.]
You see, if you are in Sahaja Yoga and in meditative mood.
If you’re in a meditative mood and if you’re in Sahaja Yoga,
then you just don’t plan,
because you know the planning is already done for you.
I know that if you take the name of “airport”, only “airport”,
you take the name and most of the men will start jumping.
They’ll go at least one hour earlier than reporting time.
Aeroplane is not going to fly out, you see, but they fear that it will fly out.
Now, if you are a Sahaja Yogi and if you are going for catching a plane,
say example, you should know what time you have to leave
and you leave at that time, you’ll reach there in time.
You don’t have to see, watch all the time, you’ll just leave at that time,
exactly at that time, you’ll leave. But also, if you are a little late,
the plane will be for you.
But you don’t want to be unkind and the Paramachaitanya looks after you.
You’ll just remember you have to go now, you leave that time.
It is so simple.
But to believe that Somebody Else is planning us is beyond our ego.
What is it?
[He says if he has to leave the planning of his life
to someone else, he’s denying his own individuality,
he’s denying that fact that he creates his own life
if he leaves the planning.]
That’s a good one, in a way is good.
Why do you want to have this kind of a feeling that you are creating the world?
Nobody’s creating. You can’t even create even a grain of clay.
No, you can’t. You can’t create anything.
What’s he saying?
[He says he’s creating his own experience now
just by raising his right hand or his left hand.]
You see you have to be little deeper to understand the significance.
Also to have faith in yourself
that supposing you become connected with the Divine Power.
Now, I’ll tell you what. Supposing you see a television. All right?
The television is connected to the mains there. All right.
Now you want to see Shakespeare, for example, that’s your plan.
But there’s another plan there going on, and when you open,
it’s not Shakespeare, it’s something else. So, what do you do?
Do you loose your identity?
Now it’s all right for him.
All right, you follow My advice and you’ll see what I am saying.
All right? Now just give it a chance. Give it a chance.
First of all, get your Realisation and give it a chance. All right?
What she is saying?
[What is the best way to go towards Self Realisation?]
That’s what we are going to do. All right? That’s a very good question.
You just wait. After all these questions are over, we’ll have that.
[He says he understands why our own actions cause
imbalances in ourselves but how about young children?
How do these diseases get caused in young children?]
Now for example, a mother is a very busy lady. When the child is there,
she’s doing all kinds of work and thinking too much, running too much.
Or the father is doing that, that has an effect on the child.
You see, human beings are delicately made.
I mean in ancient times, if a woman was to have a baby,
she used to take it very easy
and she used to read something spiritual,
she used to be thinking about her child
and feeling that motherhood within herself.
But the mother doesn’t think of the child. She just thinks she has to today go for hairdo
or she has to do something, face lifting or something like that.
I don’t know much about these things, but that’s what I’ve seen.
It’s too much of superficiality
And this has killed the beauty even of romance, you’ll be surprised.
Absolutely, it’s absurd.
These hair dressers have ruined the beauty of women in the way
because somebody likes one particular type of hair dress,
he falls in love with the hair dress. Now she changes her hair dress,
he wants to have a divorce with her.
So superficial attachments to superficial things.
There’s no deeper attachments to innate,
something so natural.
Artificial things cannot lead us anywhere,
they can never give us joy.
[He is wanting Realisation futuristic?]
Good. Good. Now what is she wanting here, this lady?
That’s what I’m going to do, I’m very happy, that part you just forget,
the rest of it. Is there any other question? Now let’s see.
Will we see a time when most of the world will have their Realisation?]
I hope so.
I would say that’s My dream. I wish, I wish that happens.
I’m actually desireless. But your desires work.
If you desire. Is the other way round. It’s not, “Thy will be done,”
but it’s “Thy will be done.”
If you desire, it will happen, it will happen.
[Is it wrong to want or desire a family and have unity in a family
and to enjoy the normal pleasures of life?]
Not at all. I mean, we are marrying so many people.
It’s not at all. It’s the best thing to have a family and children.
But not to get involved so much into your family
that you forget your ascent.
How many times you are married in previous lives
and how many children you have had in previous lives?
Now this is the time for your ascent
and your family should be complimentary.
If it is not complimentary, it’s not going to help you. It is your choice,
you’re free will. If you want to get dissolved into your own children,
and your family only and not to have any ascent,
nobody can force you, go ahead with it.
But this time is important.
This is an important time. Of course, you have to have family;
of course, you have to get married. You have to lead a very normal life.
Nothing abnormal. But if somebody is too much attached to the family,
forgets his own ascent, then I think he is missing the point.
That is the most important thing in life. Yes, please?
[Isn’t the greatest danger in the future over population?]
No, not at all. Actually, there are no imbalances
that’s why there is a population growth in some countries
and no population in some countries.
Like on the BBC gentleman came and asked Me in London,
he said, “Why do you have such a population growth?”
First, he asked, I mean they are, you know after all,
they can ask very funny questions.
They have every right to do what they like.
So, first question he asked, “Why? Wwhy is it in India
you have so much poverty?”
I said, “If you have a guest for three hundred years in your country,
what will happen to you? You’ll become a broke.”
Then he said that, “Such a population growth in Your country,
what about that?” I said, “If you can allow Me,
very humbly I would state you are responsible for that also.”
He said, “How are we responsible?”
I said, “In England, I used to hear that
two children are killed every week in England by their parents.”
He said, “No, only in London.” I said, “Really? That’s the case?
So, what child, which child would like to be born in this country?”
That’s why you see in Germany it’s minus, Sweden is minus,
Norway is minus. All these countries are having minus growth
and people are competing in committing suicide.
Switzerland, there’s a competition on.
All these countries are supposed to be affluent countries
where they have money, they can look after their children better,
they are competing in having suicides and in having minus growth.
But in India, even if you have ten children or twelve children,
love is all the time there available to them.
And what a child needs is love, not all these pomp and show
that you should have a nice cot or a nice this, but a loving mother.
That’s why they come to India. Now if you create such mothers,
they’ll come to you also.
What is he saying? Question of woman and man, he is saying what?
What exactly he did say?
[How long should a man or a woman sleep?]
You see, there’s no hard and fast rule for that,
actually. I think as you grow old, you don’t sleep so much;
I personally think that way. I sleep very little, Myself.
In the night about three hours; in the daytime about one hour or so.
But depends on, it depends.
So, for sleeping, there’s no hard and fast rule,
but whatever time you are born, that’s the time you want to sleep.
So, some people like to sleep in the morning, all right let them sleep.
And some people want to sleep in the night, let them sleep. Makes no difference.
But after coming to Sahaja Yoga, all these conditionings disappear.
And then you start behaving in a different manner.
There’s a transformation.
And then maximum time, you want to give for your meditation,
for knowing about Sahaja Yoga, and you get more time.
Actually, we should have much more time than our ancestors.
You know, we don’t have to go to the jungles to get our wood for our fire,
we don’t have to do all the rest of the things they used to do.
Poor things, they had to go for hunting.
Now we have everything in the house already made, I mean, instant. Isn’t it?
And we have the watch on all of the time watching the watch.
But we have no time. We are the worst.
They had more time than we have.
So where are we spending the time?
While coming here, I just asked him, “What do they make?”
Because I was seeing all Chinese things, Japanese things,
and then I saw lots of Greek,
and most of them were Italian things in the market, shops.
I said, “What do the Australians make?”
He said, “They make lager.”
Where do we spend our time? In the ballroom dancing? Or in the lager?
Or in some way destroying ourselves with drugs or something like that?
We have no time, we have time for drugs, all right.
Then parties, some formal things which have no meaning at all.
It conveys nothing. I have been now in London in a position
where I had to shake hands with six to seven hundred people.
And only I remember the horrible things that happen to the hand,
otherwise I don’t remember even the faces of the people.
So, there should be a better method
of developing a rapport between us,
understanding each other in much more natural way.
And then we have time, this is the time to enjoy.
But nobody enjoys because we are so time bound,
we are so time bound. Only time to enjoy we don’t have.
And that’s how whatever you people say about sleeping or waking up
and all that is that your regulation doesn’t come from the Divine.
If it is from the Divine, you just enjoy,
you just enjoy your life, you enjoy yourself.
Never feel ill or sick. And now I am sixty-seven,
every day I’m giving lectures, morning, evening.
And the smokes, the way people smoke, women,
especially in Australia, I don’t know what has gone wrong with them,
I try to go with the women, so that I’ll be saved from smoking,
they smoke more than the men even here.
So, I’ve developed a throat trouble, I hope it will be all right.
But this is what happens. Where do we spend our time?
There then you are beyond time,
into the timeless dimension enjoying yourself.
That’s the beauty we have to achieve; that state we have to reach.
All right?
What is it?
[He says, my revered father has been for the past three or four years
experiencing astral sounds,
but physically his hearing is impaired
or cut off for all practical purposes.
Twenty-four hours a day he is able to tune into
the chanting of sacred Hindu hymns, devotional music
rendered by an enchanting voice that accompanied by a violin, etcetera.
He has done no special tapas or meditation, but he is very naïve
and a simple soul. Is it because of the awakening of the Kundalini?]
No, not at all.
Not at all. All these things should not happen to you.
You don’t hear anything, you don’t see anything, you become,
you just become.
This is a subject which has to be dealt with clearly
about the dead souls and things, it’s quite a big subject.
But if you come to Sahaja Yoga, you’ll understand what happens,
how you hear these things and how astral things happen,
how your cot deaths take place. All these are all negative things
and are achieved by people who deal in the science of the dead.
Which is very important that you should get out of all these ideas
and become your Self.
Only way to know if a person is Realised is not,
the way he can handle the Kundalini,
the way he can feel the vibrations,
and the way he leads his own life.
When you go to any guru, first of all see the disciples,
how they are, how they behave, what powers they have got.
Then you accept. That’s the sign of a satguru.
Nanaka has said clearly. Guru Nanak was such an enlightened soul
and he said that, “The one who meets you, meet God, is the satguru.”
Everybody is not a guru.
So, should we now have the Realisation?
[Hindi]
That’s for only Indians.
Indians abroad.
Now should we now finish that?
Can we take out our shoes?
Because we have to take the help of the Mother Earth.
As I’ve told you, it cannot be forced.
I respect your freedom, respect your freedom. It’s your free will.
If you want to have your Realisation only you can have,
otherwise you cannot. It cannot be forced on you.
So those who do not want should leave the hall
to be civil to other people.
Otherwise you are welcome.
There are two conditions in Sahaja Yoga,
at least when you are getting your Realisation.
First is to forget your past, to forgive yourself.
You should be pleasantly placed towards yourself,
pleasantly placed towards yourself.
And second one is that you have to forgive everyone.
As I told you yesterday, whether you forgive or don’t forgive,
you don’t do anything. Actually, if you don’t forgive,
then you play into wrong hands. So just neglect it, completely.
Don’t worry about it. And in general, you should say,
“I forgive everyone.” Just say in general, “I forgive everyone.”
That’s all.
Not to count how many people you have to forgive,
not to know about everyone, what they have said to you,
but just forgive in general. That’s all.
So, the first one is to forget your past.
That means not to feel guilty at all.
You’re not to feel guilty. After all, you are a human being
and human beings can only commit mistakes. You’re not gods.
So, what does it matter?
There’s nothing to bother you on that point, should not.
So please forgive yourself and forgive others.
That’s very important.
These are the two simple conditions. But mentally, you should accept them.
Now, we have to put both our feet little away from each other,
because you know there are two powers within us, left and right.
And we use our left hand symbolically to suggest
that we want our Self Realisation and this is the power of desire,
not of Pure Desire, but desire.
And we use our right hand which is the power of action
to nourish our centres on the left-hand side.
We’ll be nourishing our left-hand centres only.
So now you please put your left hand,
comfortably the way you want to put it, it will hardly take ten minutes,
and use your right hand, as I show you now
and then we have to close our eyes.
First, put it on your heart.
This is the centre where resides the Spirit,
so is a very important centre.
Then you take down your right hand in the upper portion
of your abdomen on the left-hand side which is the centre of your mastery
created by great masters.
Now take down your right hand again
to the lower portion of your abdomen.
It is the centre –
I hope you can see it, just come forward a little bit if you don’t mind –
please, thank you.
This is the centre of Pure Knowledge, Pure Knowledge
that acts on your central nervous system.
Then you raise again your hand up
on to the upper portion of your abdomen on the left-hand side,
press it hard. Then, on to your heart.
Then into the corner of your neck and your head.
Press it as back as possible and turn your head to your right.
This centre you catch when you feel guilty.
Now you take your hand and put it on your forehead.
And put down your head on it, press it hard.
This is the centre to forgive others.
Take your right hand on the back side of your head
and please raise your head towards the sky.
This is the centre to ask for forgiveness from Divine without feeling guilty.
Then stretch your palm.
Put the centre of your palm on top of the fontanel bone area
which was a soft bone in your childhood.
Bend your head.
Now, stretch your fingers outward,
outward as much as you can, put a pressure on your scalp,
and move your scalp clockwise.
Seven times very slowly.
Now, that’s all we have to do.
Now you can close your eyes, put your left hand towards Me.
Be careful, you keep your feet apart.
Those who are sitting on the ground are all right.
And now close your eyes. You can take out your spectacles if you want to,
because don’t have to open the eyes till I tell you.
Now, please put your left hand towards Me,
and right hand on your heart.
Now close your eyes. Please don’t open them till I tell you.
Here you have to ask Me a question,
a very important question.
You can call me “Mother” or you can call Me “Shri Mataji”,
whatever you like, very important question.
Ask a question three times in your heart, not loudly, please:
“Mother, am I the Spirit?”
“Mother, am I the Spirit?” Ask this question three times.
If you are the Spirit,
you are your own guide, you are your own master.
So now please bring down your hand, right hand,
in the upper portion of your abdomen on the left-hand side,
press it hard, and here, ask another question three times,
“Mother, am I my own master?”
Ask this question three times: “Mother, am I my own master?”
Now, as I told you, I respect your freedom,
and you have a free will.
I cannot force Pure Knowledge on you, it cannot be.
You have to ask for it. So now take your right hand
in the lower portion of your abdomen on the left-hand side
and ask Me,
“Mother, please give me Pure Knowledge.”
Six times, because this centre has got six petals.
“Mother, please give me Pure Knowledge.
As soon as you ask this question, the Kundalini starts moving upward.
So now we have to nourish the upper centres
to make Its movement, Her movement, faster.
So please raise your right hand
on the upper portion of your abdomen on the left-hand side,
press it hard and here you say with full confidence,
with full confidence you say, “Mother, I am my own master.”
Please say it ten times, “Mother, I am my own master.”
These things remove your conditionings
from wrong teachings.
Now you raise your hand,
the most important question
that is you are not your body, you are not your intelligence,
you’re not your emotions, you are not your conditionings, your ego,
your thoughts, but you are pure Spirit.
So, raise your right hand on to your heart
and say with full confidence twelve times,
full confidence please, “Mother, I am the Spirit.”
Just say that, “Mother, I am the Spirit.” Please say it twelve times.
Now, raise your right hand
to another very important area within us
where, by feeling guilty all the time,
we have harmed a very important centre.
I have to tell you that the Divine Power
is the Ocean of Knowledge and Love.
It is the Ocean of Bliss and Joy.
But above all, above all it is the Ocean of Forgiveness,
and whatever mistakes or wrongs you have done
are dissolved by the power of forgiveness.
So, raise your right hand
into the corner of your neck and your shoulder
and turn your head to your right.
Here you have to say with full confidence sixteen times,
“Mother, I’m not guilty at all.”
Again, you say, “Mother, I am not guilty at all.”
Sixteen times.
I’ve already told you whether you forgive others or not,
you’re not doing anything, it is a myth.
But if you don’t forgive others,
then you fall into the wrong hands and torture yourself for nothing.
So now, please raise your right hand onto your forehead across,
press it hard on both the sides
and put down your head as far as possible,
resting on your hand, and press it on both the sides.
This is the centre where you have to forgive,
forgive others, forgive others.
Just say, “Mother, I forgive everyone.”
Without thinking about them
or thinking about what they have done to you, just say in general,
“Mother, I forgive everyone.”
Now, how many times is not the point, from your heart.
You must say it properly. Yesterday so many didn’t say
and I had to work very hard on them. So please say it,
please say it from your heart once for all, “Mother, I forgive everyone.”
Now take back your hand on the back side of your head,
on the optic globe and now raise it higher
and let it rest on your hand.
Here you have to say for your own satisfaction,
not feeling guilty, not counting your mistakes,
“Oh Divine Power, if I have done any mistakes, please forgive me.”
Say it from your heart.
Now,
stretch your palm, keeping your left hand towards Me.
This is the most important centre. Both the feet apart from each other.
Keep yourself straight and put your right hand,
the centre of your palm, on top of the fontanel bone area,
the soft bone which you had in your childhood, and press it.
Now bend your head as much as you can, press back your fingers,
press back your thumb,
so there’s a pressure on your scalp, nicely pressurised.
Now move it, move it slowly seven times.
Here again I cannot, I’m sorry,
I cannot disrespect your freedom and free will.
You have to ask for your Self Realisation, it cannot be forced on you.
So, seven times, please say seven times,
“Mother, please give me my Self Realisation.” Please say it seven times.
Now please take down your both the hands and open your eyes slowly,
very slowly. Now watch Me without thinking.
You can do it.
Now, put up your right hand like this and bend your head
and see for yourself if there’s a cool breeze coming out of your head.
Bend your head. It is above your head, not on.
So little away from the head, try to feel if there’s a cool breeze
coming out of your head. You can take your hand a little further.
Some people have it quite away from the head.
So, see for yourself if there’s a cool breeze coming out.
Now, put the left hand towards Me and put down your head.
Now see for yourself, again with the right hand,
if there’s a cool breeze coming out of your head.
Some people will get heat coming out, doesn’t matter,
it will later on be followed by cool breeze also.
You see yourself if there is the cool breeze coming.
Bend your head properly, that’s important.
Now, again put your right hand towards Me
and bend your head. Now don’t doubt. The breeze is coming from inside
and not from the air conditioner, so see for yourself.
Again, this is the Cool Breeze of the Holy Ghost,
this Kundalini is the Holy Ghost. Now see.
Now raise your both the hands towards the sky,
push back your head and here you ask a question,
“Mother, is this the Cool Breeze of the Holy Ghost?”
“Mother, is this the All Pervading Power of Divine Love?”
“Mother, is this the Paramchaitanya?” Ask any one of these questions
three times.
Push back your head fully and ask this question.
Separate your hands; don’t put them together.
Separate your hands.
May God bless you. Bring down your hands, please.
You can watch Me without thinking.
Now those who have felt the cool breeze
or even a hot breeze out of their heads or on their fingertips,
please raise both your hands.
The whole of Sydney is drowned into the Ocean of Joy.
May God bless you. So, the Kundalini has sprouted,
Kundalini has come out,
you are connected with That, but you have to establish yourself.
Otherwise it would be like the marshy land
where Christ has described some seeds fell down,
they sprouted and were destroyed.
Must respect our Self Realisation, we must respect ourselves.
Now you have become saints
and you have to understand that it’s a glorious thing
that is happening to you, and you now become the instrument of God.
You can come to the follow-on program,
they have nice courses for you, something.
You don’t have to pay anything, but you have to give some time,
that’s all, and within a month you’ll find you’ll become masters.
Master of yourself and master of this art of yoga.
They’ll answer all your questions.
They’ll see to it that it works out.
Now we have very good, humble people who’ll look after you,
and they have all the knowledge, and you can also get My tapes
and things where I tell you about,
three to four thousand tapes are there only in English language,
and in Hindi, Marathi and that way.
But unless and until you are established, I would not like you
to read books about it, because then again, you’ll get lost.
So, first thing is to establish yourself fully,
so you don’t get lost into your ego, as you were saying,
or into any such trips. Better get established first,
then nothing makes you feel that way.
May God bless you all.
I’ll be coming after one year and I hope all of you will become great trees
giving the beautiful vibrations to this great country of innocence
and changing everyone.
The transformation within you will definitely help to change
so many things in this country and you’ll be amazed
how the planning of the Divine works for you every moment
and how you’re helped and looked after, guided and protected.
It’s very surprising.
May God bless you.
Yesterday I met most of you people.
Those whom I have not met and who have got Realisation,
I would like to meet. It’s already it is ten-thirty.
We had a music program.
But whom I have met is all right.
Those who haven’t got Realisation can come on one side. They can see.
Those whom I have not met and who have got Realisation,
can come and meet Me.